so now that we have seen multiple
aspects of how caches work let's
summarize them for a more realistic
cache let's say we have a 4 kilobyte
four-way set associative cache with a 64
byte line size with a right back and
right allocate right policies the
processor let's say creates 64-bit
addresses to access the cash when
accessing this cache the 64-bit address
will be divided into offset bits index
bits and tag bits first for offset bits
it's a 64 byte line so we need six bits
bits 0 through five there are six of
them are going to tell us where in the
cache block we are next we need to
determine how many sets this cache has
it's a 4 kilobyte cache that's 2 to the
12 bytes the number of blocks is that
divided by 64 4 which is 2 to the 6 so
we have 2 to the 6 blocks in the cache
it's a four-way set asstive cache which
means that every set has four blocks in
it so we divide the number of blocks
with the number of blocks in a set and
we get 2 to the 4th or 16 sets now we
know that we need four bits to tell us
which set we are in so bits six 7 8 and
nine four of them are the index the bits
that remain bits 10 through
63 54 of them are the Tag now in our
cache we will have for each block a
valid bit it's a right back hash so we
will also have a dirty bit then there
will be a tag 54 bits it's a fourway set
asstive cash so we need to pick a
replacement policy let's say the
replacement policy is lru for a four-way
set associative cache each block needs
to have a 2bit lru counter so here we
have 1 1 54 2 and then we have 64 bytes
worth of actual data as you can see we
have 58 bytes in addition to the data so
there is some overhead the cache size is
usually expressed in terms of how much
data it contains but the actual size of
the cache array is larger because it
needs to contain all these extra bits
for each line of data